A Guide to the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association, Inc. records FA085
Rockefeller Archive Center
- DLMA, Inc., 1957-1995; 2; 78.875 Cubic Feet 214 document cases
  - Bulletins and Publications, 1945-1995 1958-1973; 2.4; 3.85 Cubic Feet 12 document cases
    - Vertical File Materials (Box 206, Folder 1852)
      Miscellaneous maps, travel guides, brochures, pamphlets, guidebooks, of Lower Manhattan. Examples of Vertical File material include but are not limited to: A. Cushman & Wakefield Downtown Manhattan Office Building Map, 1982. B. "Get Into New York: Guidebook of Lower Manhattan" (Pamphlet). C. "Your Pocket Guide to NOW in New York, Introducing New York City's Heritage Trail" An Official New York City Bicentennial Publication, July 1976, (Pamphlet). D. "AIA Guide to New York City" (American Institute of Architects), c. 1967. E. Downtown Manhattan Office Building Map, Jones Lang Wooten, USA.
    - Vertical File Materials (Box 206, Folder 1853)
    - Vertical File Materials (Box 206, Folder 1854)
    - Vertical File Materials (Box 206, Folder 1855)
    - Gerald J. Morse - "A Talk-A-Walk Guide to Lower Manhattan", 1980-1989 (Box 207, Folder 1856)
      Includes manuscript, correspondence and promotion cassette, etc.
    - "Info", 1980s-1990s (Box 207, Folder 1857)
      Contains visitors information, subway maps, pocket atlas, Wall Street Club, etc.
  - Reports and Studies, 1948-1994; 2.5; 6.525 Cubic Feet 19 document cases
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically within each subject heading.
    Highlights of this subseries include reports and studies regarding many major projects recommended or advocated by the DLMA including: Battery Park City and its potential use as the site for a Lower Manhattan convention center, Lower Manhattan Expressway, the Water Street Subway, a variety of traffic and transportation reports including the DLMA brief in support of the widening of Fulton Street and copies of both the "Lower Manhattan Plan" (1966) and the subsequent "Plan for Lower Manhattan" (1993).
    Additional reports can also be found within the project records in Series 2.3.
    - Business Retention and Attraction - "A Plan for Manhattan Civic Center", June 1948 (Box 187, Folder 1873)
      Prepared by the City Planning Commission in collaboration with the Office of the President, Borough of Manhattan and other city agencies. Oversized booklet.
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "The Lower Manhattan Plan Capital Project ES-1", June 1, 1966; 2 copies (Box 187, Folder 1917)
      Wallace, McHarg, Roberts & Todd (Architects & Planners, Philadelphia). Alan M. Voorhees & Associates, Inc. (Transportation and Planning Consultants, Washington, D. C.) Prepared for the New York City Planning Commission (William F. R. Ballard, Chairman). 1 copy is the original; the other is a copy made by Sir Speedy. Both copies are oversized spiral bound booklets.
    - "South Street Seaport: A Plan for a Vital New Historic Center in Lower Manhattan" (Box 187, Folder 1938)
      Published by South Street Seaport Museum, date unknown. Oversized spiral bound volume.
    - American Stock Exchange - "AMEX Proposals for the American Stock Exchange: Expansion in Lower Manhattan", May 1977; 2 copies (Box 208, Folder 1858)
      City of New York, Department of City Planning (NYC DCP 77-03).
    - Battery Park City - "Battery Park City: New Living Space for New York", 1966; 3 copies (Box 208, Folder 1859)
      "A proposal for creating a site for residential and business facilities in Lower Manhattan."
    - Battery Park City - "Alternate Westside Highway Reconstruction Alignments at Battery Park City, New York, New York, Evaluations, Recommendations", March 30, 1973; 2 copies (Box 208, Folder 1860)
      Prepared for Battery Park City Authority by: Harrison & Abramovitz (Architects), Tams Gibbs & Hill (Architects and Engineers), Mueser Rutledge Wentworth and Johnson (Consulting Engineers).
    - Battery Park City - "A Reexamination of Battery Park City" (DRAFT), April 20, 1979; 1 copy (Box 208, Folder 1861)
      Vollmer Associates, Inc. prepared for D-LMA.
    - Battery Park City - "A Reexamination of Battery Park City", April 24, 1979; 2 copies (Box 208, Folder 1862)
      Vollmer Associates, Inc. prepared for D-LMA, Inc..
    - Battery Park City - Report - Battery Park City Authority, October 28, 1979 (Box 208, Folder 1863)
    - Battery Park City - "Battery Park City Draft Summary Report and 1979 Master Plan" (Box 209, Folder 1864)
      Prepared for Battery Park City Authority by Alexander Cooper Associates. October 1979. Prepared by Beyer Blinder Belle (Architects and Planners).
    - Battery Park City - "Battery Park City - 1979 Master Plan: Financial Analysis", November 7, 1979 (Box 209, Folder 1865)
      Easdil Realty, Inc. Prepared for: Battery Park City Authority.
    - Battery Park City - "Localized Transit Trip Generation and Impact Analysis, World Trade Center/Battery Park City Area", 1986-1987 (Box 209, Folder 1866)
      Prepared for the New York City Department of City Planning. Submitted by: Polytechnic Institute in association with Urbitran Associates, Inc. and Helen Neuhaus Consulting. The following portions of this study are available: A. Technical Memorandum 2B - "Survey Design and Execution and Summary Results," September 1986. B. Technical Memorandum 2C - "Physical and Operational Characteristics of Sidewalks and Transit Stations," February 1986. C. Technical Memorandum 2D - "Current Travel Patterns and Level of Service Analysis," September 1986.
    - Battery Park City - "Localized Transit Trip Generation and Impact Analysis, World Trade Center/Battery Park City Area", 1986-1987 (Box 209, Folder 1867)
      Prepared for the New York City Department of City Planning. Submitted by: Polytechnic Institute in association with Urbitran Associates, Inc. and Helen Neuhaus Consulting. The following portions of this study are available: D. Technical Memorandum 3A - "Transit Travel Demand Methodology," January 1987. E. Technical Memorandum 3B - "Generation and Allocation of Trips Resulting from Proposed New Developments in Lower Manhattan," April 1987. F. Technical Memorandum 4 - "Development Impacts on Transit Stations and Study Intersections," April 1987.
    - Battery Park City - "Localized Transit Trip Generation and Impact Analysis, World Trade Center/Battery Park City Area", 1986-1987 (Box 209, Folder 1868)
      Prepared for the New York City Department of City Planning. Submitted by: Polytechnic Institute in association with Urbitran Associates, Inc. and Helen Neuhaus Consulting. The following portions of this study are available: G. Technical Memorandum 5A - "Preliminary Improvement Formulation," May 1987. H. Technical Memorandum 5B - "Detailed Improvement Plan," June 1987. I. Technical Memorandum 6 - "Implementation Strategy," June 1987.
    - Battery Park City - "Localized Transit Trip Generation and Impact Analysis, World Trade Center/Battery Park City Area", 1986-1987 (Box 209, Folder 1869)
      Prepared for the New York City Department of City Planning. Submitted by: Polytechnic Institute in association with Urbitran Associates, Inc. and Helen Neuhaus Consulting. The following portions of this study are available: J. Draft, Final Report, August 1987.
    - Business Retention and Attraction - "Survey of Executive Opinion Regarding Downtown-Lower Manhattan" - Group Attitudes Company, New York City, July 5, 1973 (Box 210, Folder 1870)
      Commissioned by the D-LMA, Inc.
    - Business Retention and Attraction - "Survey on Business Retention and Attraction in Lower Manhattan" (DLMA), July 19, 1993 (Box 210, Folder 1871)
      Deloitte and Touche developed and administered the survey for the DLMA.
    - Business Retention and Attraction - "City Hall Park Underpass Feasibility Study" Prepared for Department of Highways, Transportation Administration, New York City, December 1972 (Box 210, Folder 1872)
      Carroll and Frankfort Consulting Engineers.
    - Convention Center - "New York City Convention and Exhibition Center - Feasibility Study", May 1976; 2 copies (Box 210, Folder 1874)
      The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. Both copies are bound with staples.
    - Convention Center - "Estimated Market for a Convention Exposition Center to be Located at Battery Park City" - Arthur D. Little, Inc., May 25, 1976 (Box 210, Folder 1875)
      C-79562.
    - Convention Center - "Evaluation of New York City Convention and Exhibition Center at Battery Park City" - Rough Draft (Box 210, Folder 1876)
      Prepared for D-LMA, Inc. Prepared by: Vollmer Associates.
    - Convention Center - "Evaluation of New York City Convention and Exhibition Center at Battery Park City" - Working Draft, 2 copies (Box 210, Folder 1877)
    - Convention Center - "Evaluation of New York City Convention and Exhibition Center at Battery Park City" - Justin J. Murphy Copies, 2 copies (Box 211, Folder 1878)
      Prepared for D-LMA, Inc. Prepared by: Vollmer Associates. With accompanying correspondence.
    - Convention Center - "Evaluation of New York City Convention and Exhibition Center at Battery Park City", September 24, 1976; 2 copies (Box 211, Folder 1879)
      Prepared for D-LMA, Inc. Prepared by: Vollmer Associates. Appears to be the final version of this report.
    - Convention Center - "Comparative Evaluation - Proposed Convention Center Sites - Battery Park City, Coliseum, 44th Street, 30th Street Railroad Yard, Times Square" - Working Draft, March 25, 1977 (Box 211, Folder 1880)
      Vollmer Associates. Prepared for D-LMA, Inc.
    - Convention Center - "Comparative Evaluation - Proposed Convention Center Sites - Battery Park City, Coliseum, 44th Street, 30th Street Railroad Yard, Times Square", March 31, 1977; 2 copies (Box 211, Folder 1881)
    - Convention Center - "Comparative Evaluation - Proposed Convention Center Sites - Battery Park City, Coliseum, 44th Street, 30th Street Railroad Yard, Times Square", March 31, 1977; 2 copies (Box 211, Folder 1882)
      Vollmer Associates. Prepared for D-LMA, Inc. With appendix A-L. One copy is handsigned by Justin J. Murphy, D-LMA President.
    - Convention Center - "Lower Manhattan: The Best Site for New York City's Convention Center", 3 copies (Box 212, Folder 1883)
      Brochure. DLMA, Inc.
    - Convention Center - Brochure Mailings, 1977 (Box 212, Folder 1884)
    - East River Landing Transit Impact Study, 1986-1988 (Box 212, Folder 1885)
      Prepared for New York City, Department of City Planning, Transportation Division.
    - Emergency Management - Federal Emergency Management Administration (FEMA), 1993-1994 (Box 212, Folder 1886)
      Includes: A. "Emergency Management Guide for Business and Industry" FEMA 141, October 1993. B. Emergency Management Institute, Catalog, 1993-1994 C. Metropolitan New York Hurricane Transportation Survey, 1994. (U. S. Army Corps of Engineers, FEMA, National Weather Service, New York/New Jersey/Connecticut State Emergency Management
    - Financial District - Information Summary, March 1963 (Box 212, Folder 1887)
      Prepared by D-LMA, Inc.
    - Fulton Street - "Brief in Support of Fulton Street Widening", 1961 (Box 212, Folder 1888)
      Submitted by D-LMA, Inc. [to Board of Estimate]
    - Global Securities - U. S. Congress, Office of Technology Assessment - "Trading Around the Clock: Global Securities Markets and Information Technology - Background Paper", July 1990 (Box 212, Folder 1889)
      OTA-BP-CIT-66 (Washington DC: US Government Printing Office).
    - Greenwich Street Development District - "Special Greenwich Street Development District", 1971; 2 copies (Box 212, Folder 1890)
      Office of the Lower Manhattan Development, Office of the Mayor (City of New York)
    - Housing - Study on Market Potential by James Felt and Company, 1967 (Box 212, Folder 1891)
      1967-1968.
    - Housing - "Housing Potential 1967-1982 - Lower Manhattan Proposed Waterfront Community on the Hudson", November 1, 1967; 2 copies (Box 213, Folder 1892)
      James Felt & Company, Inc. Prepared for D-LMA, Inc.
    - Housing - Housing Study - James Felt and Company, 1971 (Box 213, Folder 1893)
      1971-1973
    - Housing - "Housing Potential Lower Manhattan", December 1, 1971; 2 copies (Box 213, Folder 1894)
      James Felt & Company, Inc. Prepared for D-LMA, Inc. One copy belonged to Justin J. Murphy; the other copy is accompanied by correspondence of December 29, 1971.
    - Hudson River - Hudson River Valley Greenway Council, 1990-1991 (Box 213, Folder 1895)
      Folder includes: A. "Draft Study for a Hudson River Valley Greenway." Hudson River Valley Greenway Council. April 1990 (1 copy). B. "A Hudson River Valley Greenway" - A report to Gov. Cuomo and the New York State Legislature. Hudson River Valley Greenway Council, February 1991 (1 copy).
    - Hudson River - "A Vision for the Hudson River Waterfront Park - Recommendations of the West Side Waterfront Panel", November 1, 1990 (Box 213, Folder 1896)
      A report to Governor Mario M. Cuomo and Mayor David N. Dinkins.
    - Hudson River - "A Vision for the Hudson River Waterfront Park - Recommendations of the West Side Waterfront Panel" - Report Appendix, Volume I, November 1, 1990 (Box 214, Folder 1897)
      A report to Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and Mayor David N. Dinkins.
    - Hudson River - "A Vision for the Hudson River Waterfront Park - Recommendations of the West Side Waterfront Panel" - Report Appendix, Volume II, November 1, 1990 (Box 214, Folder 1898)
    - Landmarks - "To Preserve A Heritage" - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 214, Folder 1899)
    - Landmarks - "To Preserve A Heritage: The Restoration and Utilization of Historic Sites in Lower Manhattan", 1975; 3 copies (Box 214, Folder 1900)
      Inside back of Title Page: "The Mayors Office of Lower Manhattan. Development in cooperation with the New York City Bicentennial Corporation. A publication to honor the nation's 200th year, made possible by grants from corporations and institutions in New York City." One copy has a different colored cover.
    - Landmarks - "Recommended Scheme for the Marble Palace: Rehabilitation and Restoration of 280 Broadway and Related Design Alternatives", January 1991 (Box 214, Folder 1901)
      Prepared for the New York City Department of General Services (Kenneth J. Knuckles, Commissioner).
    - "Lower Manhattan Bus Distribution Facilities Study", 1987-1989 (Box 214, Folder 1902)
      Report is dated 1987.
    - "Lower Manhattan Bus Loop Implementation Study" - Final Report, June 1994; 1 copy (Box 214, Folder 1903)
      Development of City Planning, City of New York.
    - Lower Manhattan Cutural Council (LMCC) - Report - "Capital, Creativity, Community: Realizing A New Vision for Lower Manhattan", 1992 (Box 214, Folder 1904)
      Hugh O'Neill, Urban Research Center, New York University.
    - Lower Manhattan Expressway - "Lower Manhattan Expressway: An Essential Key to the Business Growth and Job Opportunities in Lower Manhattan and New York City", July 1, 1964; 2 copies (Box 215, Folder 1905)
    - Lower Manhattan Expressway - "Need for Lower Manhattan Expressway", July 15, 1964; 3 copies (Box 215, Folder 1906)
      Madigan-Hyland, Inc. (Consulting Engineers, New York City). Prepared for the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority. One copy has ring binding; the other two copies are semi-hard bound. One copy has the initials of Justin Murphy and contains a map insert from November 1959.
    - Lower Manhattan Expressway - "Lower Manhattan Elevated Expressway", November 15, 1965; 2 copies (Box 215, Folder 1907)
      Vollmer Associates, Inc. Prepared for the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority.
    - Lower Manhattan Expressway - "The Lower Manhattan Expressway Project", July 13, 1966 (Box 215, Folder 1908)
      Madigan-Hyland, Inc. (Consulting Engineers, New York City). Prepared for the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority.
    - Lower Manhattan Expressway - Truck Study, 1969 (Box 215, Folder 1909)
      Vollmer Associates, Inc. Prepared for D-LMA, Inc.
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - "Banning the Car Downtown - Footnotes #3", December 1976 (Box 215, Folder 1910)
      Department of Housing and Urban Development, National Endowment for the Arts, President's Council on Environmental Quality. HUD-PDR-192-3.
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - "The Rediscovery of the Pedestrian: 12 European Cities - Footnotes 2", December 1976 (Box 215, Folder 1911)
      Department of Housing and Urban Development, National Endowment for the Arts, President's Council on Environmental Quality. HUD-PDR-192-2.
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - Broad Street - Proposed Sidewalk Widening, 1971 (Box 215, Folder 1912)
      Office of the Lower Manhattan Development, Office of the Mayor (City of New York).
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - Chambers Street Study, 1974 (Box 215, Folder 1913)
      Office of the Lower Manhattan Development, The Lower Manhattan Transportation Study Group.
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - Lower Manhattan People Mover, 1971-1973 (Box 215, Folder 1914)
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - Lower Manhattan People Mover, 1976-1977 (Box 215, Folder 1915)
    - Lower Manhattan - Pedestrians - Lower Manhattan People Mover, 1985-1989 (Box 216, Folder 1916)
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "Planning for Lower Manhattan" - A Report to the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Associates, Inc., 1968-1969; 2 copies (Box 216, Folder 1918)
      Vollmer Associates. Submitted by Vollmer Associates to D-LMA Planning Committee Chairman Desmond Crawford, December 16, 1968. The reports submitted to D-LMA, Planning Committee by Vollmer Associates on December 16, 1968 and then subsequently submitted to David Rockefeller and Edmund Wagner on January 7, 1969 are both in conformance with a contract dated July 8, 1968.
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "Planning for Lower Manhattan" - A Report to the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Associates, Inc., 1968-1969; 2 copies (Box 216, Folder 1919)
      Vollmer Associates. Submitted by D-LMA Planning Committee Chairman Desmond Crawford to D-LMA Chairman David Rockefeller and D-LMA President Edmund Wagner, January 7, 1969. The reports submitted to D-LMA, Planning Committee by Vollmer Associates on December 16, 1968 and then subsequently submitted to David Rockefeller and Edmund Wagner on January 7, 1969 are both in conformance with a contract dated July 8, 1968.
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "Planning for Lower Manhattan" - A Report to the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Associates, Inc., 1968-1969; 2 copies (Box 217, Folder 1920)
      Vollmer Associates. Submitted by D-LMA Planning Committee Chairman Desmond Crawford to D-LMA Chairman David Rockefeller and D-LMA President Edmund Wagner, January 7, 1969. 1 copy given to D-LMA by Edward Moloney (Vollmer Associates Library). The reports submitted to D-LMA, Planning Committee by Vollmer Associates on December 16, 1968 and then subsequently submitted to David Rockefeller and Edmund Wagner on January 7, 1969 are both in conformance with a contract dated July 8, 1968.
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "Plan for Lower Manhattan", October 1993; 2 copies (Box 217, Folder 1921)
      Prepared by the Department of City Planning with the support of the New York City Economic Development Corporation and the Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association. NYC DCP93-24.
    - Lower Manhattan Plan - "A Plan for Revitalization of Lower Manhattan", 1995; 3 copies (Box 217, Folder 1922)
      Rudolph W. Giuliani, Mayor.
    - "Lower Manhattan Waterfront", June 1975; 2 copies (Box 217, Folder 1923)
      Office of the Mayor, City of New York and Office of Lower Manhattan Development. Includes Battery Park City district, Manhattan Landing Development District and South Street Seaport District.
    - New York City - Economy - "The City in Transition: Prospects and Policies for New York", 1978 (Box 217, Folder 1924)
      The final report of the Temporary Commission on City Finances. Arco Press, New York Times Company, New York.
    - New York City - Economy - "Analysis of the New York City Economy", 1994 (Box 217, Folder 1925)
      A. "Analysis of the New York City Economy," May 5, 1994, Technical Memorandum 1-95. State of New York, Office of the State Comptroller H. Carl McCall (State Comptroller). Office of the State Deputy Comptroller for the City of New York Rosemary Scanlon (Asst. Deputy Comptroller for the City of New York). B. "Analysis of the New York City Economy," Technical Memorandum 2-95. State of New York Office of the State Comptroller. Office of the State Deputy Comptroller for the City of New York, October 14, 1994.
    - New York City - Infrastructure (Box 218, Folder 1926)
      A. "Building New York City for the 21st Century." Report for the New York Building Congress, Public Construction Task Force for the City of New York. Funding for the report was provided by: The Council of Business and Labor for the Economic Development of New York and the New York Building Congress. Date: c. 1988. B. "Coming to Grips with some Major Problems in the Construction Industry," Vol. II. Issues by the Business Roundtable, 1978. C. "The Age of New York City Infrastructure: Water Supply, Water Disposal, Bridges, Transit, Streets." The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, August 1991. D. "Smart Money - Now is the Time to Invest in the Physical City." The Infrastructure Institute at the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1992.
    - New York City - Peddlers/Vendors - "Balancing Safety and Sales on City Streets", February 1991 (Box 218, Folder 1927)
      A report on street vending to Mayor David N. Dinkins. Task Force on General Vendors, Department of Consumer Affairs.
    - New York City - Planning (Box 218, Folder 1928)
      A. Urban Design - "The Threatened City: A Report on the Design of the City of New York by the Mayor's Task Force" (February 7, 1967). B. "Report of the Board of Water Supply (City of New York) to the Board of Estimate on City Tunnel No. 3, Stage 2. May 23, 1973. C. "New York City Zoning: The Need for Reform." Authors - Katherine Kennedy, Mitchell S. Bernard (Natural Resources Defense Council), and Ethel Paley, Barbara Reach and Sandor E. Katz (Women's City Club of New York), June 1989. D. "Planning New York City 1991-1992" Department of City Planning. DCP #91-22, October 1991.
    - New York State - Targets of Economic Opportunity: A Strategy for Economic Development in New York State, July 1979; 2 copies (Box 218, Folder 1929)
      New York State Office of the Governor.
    - New York/New Jersey Metropolitan Region (Box 218, Folder 1930)
      A. "Regional Economy - Review 1993, Outlook 1994 for the New York-New Jersey Metropolitan Region." The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, March 1994. B. "Proceedings of the Regional Policy Roundtables - Prospects and Strategies for the 21st Century." The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, 1993-1994. C. "Demographic Trends in the New York-New Jersey Metropolitan Region - Income Distribution and Poverty" (Analysis of Key Findings from 1990 Census of Population). Prepared by: Strategic Information Division, Office of Economic & Policy Analysis, The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, January 1994.
    - Office Buildings (Box 219, Folder 1931)
      A. "The Corporate Headquarters in New York City." Prepared by the Conservation of Human Resources Project, Columbia University, December 1997. B. Downtown Office Building Map. Cross & Brown Company, 1978. C. "Feasibility and Desirability of Converting Office Buildings to Apartment Houses in Lower Manhattan" -- A thesis presented to the faculty of Architecture and Planning, Columbia University by Nadine Peyser, April 1994.
    - Office Buildings - Studley Reports, 1974-1976 (Box 219, Folder 1932)
    - Operation Sail (OpSail), 1976, 1986 (Box 219, Folder 1933)